Welcome back.
Let's now very quickly learn what HTML actually is
and what we can do with it.
So basically HTML stands for Hypertext Markup language and
remembered how we learned earlier that HTML is one of the
core web technologies along with CSS and JavaScript.
Right, now,
HTML is a markup language that we web developers can use to
structure and describe the entire content of any webpage.
So notice how I said markup language,
because HTML is really not a programming language.
It's a markup language because we use it
to describe something.
And in the case of HTML,
we do describe content using elements.
So we have different elements that we can use to describe
different types of content. So for example,
we have the P element that we already used in the lecture
where we created our very first webpage.
And so we use the P element there to create a paragraph,
but we really have all kinds of different elements.
So elements to create links, to create page headings,
images, video, and a lot more,
as you will learn throughout this section.
And basically throughout the entire course,
then, as we also learned in that lecture
where we built our very first webpage,
web browsers, such as Google Chrome,
do essentially understand HTML code and can render it
as a final website, so website that we can see
in the browser.
Okay.
So this is essentially what HTML is and
what we can do with it.
But now let's just zoom in a little bit and take a look at
the anatomy of a HTML element.
So basically take a look at the building blocks of
each HTML element.
And again, we are looking at the paragraph element here,
as you can see by the P.
And so all of this here is actually the element itself.
Now an HTML element is usually made up of three parts.
First is the opening tag, which is the name of the element.
So in this case,
it's the P wrapped in the less than in the greater den
symbols, probably they have some other names,
but that's how I like to call the symbols.
So it's less than P and then greater than.
Then, after that,
we have basically the content of the element.
So in this example, that is just text,
but there might be other types of content.
For example, an element can contain in itself,
another element which we then call a child element.
Also some elements such as images have actually
no content at all and have only an opening tech.
And all of this will of course become
very intuitive as we start writing HTML.
This is just so that,
you know what I'm talking about when I speak of opening tag
or closing tag or content, and speaking of the closing tag,
it is basically the same as the opening tag,
but with a slash.
So it opens its paragraph element simply with the P
and we then close it with slash P, okay.
Now for elements that do not have content
such as the image element that I mentioned before,
we actually omit the closing tag. So in that case,
we only have the opening tag and that's it,
and we will see that in action of course
once we start integrating images into a webpage.
Okay, and that's really,
all you need in order to start learning HTML and practice,
which is exactly what we will do in the next lecture.